<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
        <title>BUGS</title>
        <description>BUGS - Congwei Chen</description>
        <link></link>
        <link></link>
        <lastBuildDate>2023-05-07T14:18:52-04:00</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>2023-05-07T14:18:52-04:00</pubDate>
        <ttl>1800</ttl>


        <item>
                <title>Efficient</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;: Boxi Lin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisory Committee:&lt;/strong&gt; Lei Sun (Supervisor), Lisa Strug, and Shelley Bull&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date and Time&lt;/strong&gt;:  Tuesday, December 20, 2022, 10am-12noon EST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: 155 College Street, Health Science Building, Room 790&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The genetic architecture of a complex trait may differ among subpopulations of a studied population. In genetic association studies, stratified and joint analysis strategies have been applied to incorporate heterogeneity. However, there is no uniformly most powerful test, and their performance will depend on the underlying genetic model. We aim to develop robust association testing methods that remain powerful under various patterns of heterogeneity by leveraging heterogeneity through the lens of interaction. We first propose second-order meta-analysis combing evidence from each subpopulation by taking the sum of Z-scores. We show the analytical connection between this meta-analysis is equivalent to mega-analysis approach based on weighted regression. Then we will conduct large-scale real data application to discover genetic association hidden in previous GWAS with stratified design or ignoring the potential heterogeneity and heteroskedasticity. Apart from identifying genetic effect in any of the groups, we also aim to develop meta-analysis for detecting the presence of genetic effect heterogeneity between groups. Lastly, we plan to apply the joint location-scale (JLS) testing framework detecting genetic association under heterogeneity due to unknown environmental factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All are welcome!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>/proposal%20defense/2022/12/23/Efficient</link>
                <guid>/proposal%20defense/2022/12/23/Efficient</guid>
                <pubDate>2022-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Robust Genetic Association Testing Approaches Accounting For Heterogeneity copy</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;: Boxi Lin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisory Committee:&lt;/strong&gt; Lei Sun (Supervisor), Lisa Strug, and Shelley Bull&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date and Time&lt;/strong&gt;:  Tuesday, December 20, 2022, 10am-12noon EST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: 155 College Street, Health Science Building, Room 790&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The genetic architecture of a complex trait may differ among subpopulations of a studied population. In genetic association studies, stratified and joint analysis strategies have been applied to incorporate heterogeneity. However, there is no uniformly most powerful test, and their performance will depend on the underlying genetic model. We aim to develop robust association testing methods that remain powerful under various patterns of heterogeneity by leveraging heterogeneity through the lens of interaction. We first propose second-order meta-analysis combing evidence from each subpopulation by taking the sum of Z-scores. We show the analytical connection between this meta-analysis is equivalent to mega-analysis approach based on weighted regression. Then we will conduct large-scale real data application to discover genetic association hidden in previous GWAS with stratified design or ignoring the potential heterogeneity and heteroskedasticity. Apart from identifying genetic effect in any of the groups, we also aim to develop meta-analysis for detecting the presence of genetic effect heterogeneity between groups. Lastly, we plan to apply the joint location-scale (JLS) testing framework detecting genetic association under heterogeneity due to unknown environmental factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All are welcome!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>/proposal%20defense/2022/12/22/Robust-Genetic-Association-Testing-Approaches-Accounting-for-Heterogeneity-copy</link>
                <guid>/proposal%20defense/2022/12/22/Robust-Genetic-Association-Testing-Approaches-Accounting-for-Heterogeneity copy</guid>
                <pubDate>2022-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Precision Public Health In Canada, hurdles And Opportunities</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;: Dr. Zahra Shakeri, University of Toronto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date and Time&lt;/strong&gt;:  Tuesday, November 8, 2022, 3-4 PM EST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: https://www.dlsph.utoronto.ca/event/biostatistics-seminar-series-with-dr-zahra-shakeri-on-precision-public-health/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract. Data suggests that 1 in 4 deaths of Canadians younger than 75 are potentially preventable by reducing the prevalence of known risk factors (e.g., poor lifestyle, smoking) and improving the effectiveness of health care and disease prevention policies. Data from diverse populations will provide a more granular and robust prediction of these risk factors and ensure an unbiased assessment. Canada’s rich provincial, territorial, and national health and social, and environmental data provides a unique opportunity to leverage and integrate these disparate data sources to link public health data more efficiently with clinical data, jump-starting the operationalization of precision public health to provide tailored health care to patients and accelerate early detection of population health issues. In this talk, I will focus on the requirements and challenges of developing an intelligent and robust framework to bridge the gaps between EHRs and public health information needs and discuss the implementation of these requirements by providing examples of digital public health surveillance and EHR data analysis using natural language processing, machine learning, and data visualization techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All are welcome!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>/seminar/2022/11/11/Precision-Public-Health-in-Canada,-Hurdles-and-Opportunities</link>
                <guid>/seminar/2022/11/11/Precision-Public-Health-in-Canada, Hurdles-and-Opportunities</guid>
                <pubDate>2022-11-11T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>November Bugs Potluck Social</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date and Time&lt;/strong&gt;:  Thursday, November 24, 2022, 4:30am-7:30noon EST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: 155 College Street, Health Science Building, Room 700&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello DLSPH biostatistics students!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s Eric again from the BUGS exec team, messaging to inform you of the Potluck Social Event taking place this November! This is to make up for October’s cancelled Halloween potluck, and BUGS is happy to have settled the date for the new event. Come join us on Thursday, November 24th from 4:30pm-7:30pm, in HS700 (the seventh floor student lounge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what’s in store for the evening!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potluck: You’re encouraged to bring food you would like to share with others at the event! Home-baked goods, or just one of your favourite purchased snacks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Games: Feel free to bring any board/card games you’d like to play with your colleagues while we hang out in the lounge!
All of the above are optional – you will be welcomed with open arms if you arrive empty-handed 😊&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note we have decided to drop the costume part of this event, since it is no longer occurring in Halloween season. We’re excited to see everyone’s costumes next Halloween though! 
See you soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>/social%20event/2022/11/09/November-BUGS-Potluck-Social</link>
                <guid>/social%20event/2022/11/09/November-BUGS-Potluck-Social</guid>
                <pubDate>2022-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Vol Methods</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;: Dr. Anna Heath, University of Toronto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date and Time&lt;/strong&gt;:  Tuesday, November 1, 2022, 3-4 PM EST&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: 155 College Street, Health Science Building, Room 790&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear BUGS,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Anna Heath ( https://www.dlsph.utoronto.ca/faculty-profile/heath-anna/; https://lab.research.sickkids.ca/heath/) will be giving an informal presentation on her current research and opportunities for students (incl. thesis and research projects and RA etc), and you are invited to join us tomorrow  (November 1) afternoon, 3-4pm, in HSB 790.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof Heath’s research focuses on developing new, innovative statistical methods to design, prioritise and analyse clinical research within a Bayesian framework. She is particularly interested in applying methods from decision theory, the science of determining the best course of action when the consequence of each action is uncertain, to the conception, design and analysis of clinical trials. She has projects focusing on both applied and theoretical developments for clinical trial design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wendy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All are welcome!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>/misc/2022/11/01/Vol-Methods</link>
                <guid>/misc/2022/11/01/Vol-Methods</guid>
                <pubDate>2022-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Develop Novel Statistical Methods For Analyzing Longread Sequencing Data</title>
                <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;: Gengming He&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supervisory Committee:&lt;/strong&gt;  Lisa Strug (Supervisor), Lei Sun, and Dehan Kong&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date and Time:&lt;/strong&gt;  Wednesday, September 14, 2022, 1-3pm EDT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoom Meeting Info:&lt;/strong&gt;  https://utoronto.zoom.us/j/83156954317&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;  Phase information and variable number tandem repeat (VNTR) are known to contribute to genetic diseases but were missing from most genetic association studies due to the constrains of short-read sequencing assays, limit our understanding of their roles in disease development. Recently developed long-read sequencing technology is capable of measuring phase information and complete VNTR sequences at individual level and novel statistical methods need to be tailored to incorporate this new data into analysis. In this project, we aim to 1) utilized the phase information to detect cis-acting effects between genetic variants based on a matrix regression framework and 2) develop a reference-free association method based on k-mers to detect disease related VNTRs.  For objective 1), we introduced a cis-interaction matrix to analyze genotypes and their phase information simultaneously. Simulation studies demonstrated that this approach has improved power of detecting cis-acting effect comparing to current genotype-only methods. For objective 2), we developed a k-mer based method to genotype VNTR number of repeats without using the reference genome (reference-free). Genotyping error could occur due to the point mutations in the region. We proposed a score statistics to remedy its impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All are welcome!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>/proposal%20defense/2022/09/14/Develop-Novel-Statistical-Methods-for-Analyzing-Longread-Sequencing-Data</link>
                <guid>/proposal%20defense/2022/09/14/Develop-Novel-Statistical-Methods-for-Analyzing-Longread-Sequencing-Data</guid>
                <pubDate>2022-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>


</channel>
</rss>
